When Dorothy was a little girl,
عندما كانت دورثي صغيرة،
she was fascinated by her goldfish.
كانت مسحورة بسمكتها الذهبية.
Her father explained to her that fish swim by quickly wagging their tails
أباها شرح لها ، بأن السمك يسبح بهز أذياله بسرعة
to propel themselves through the water.
ليدفع نفسه عبر الماء.
Without hesitation, little Dorothy responded,
بدون تردد أجابت دورثي الصغيرة
"Yes, Daddy, and fish swim backwards by wagging their heads."
"نعم ، يا أبي والسمك يسبح للخلف بهز رأسه."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In her mind, it was a fact as true as any other.
في عقلها لقد كانت حقيقة صحيحة مثلها مثل أي شيء آخر.
Fish swim backwards by wagging their heads.
السمك يسبح للخلف بهز رأسه.
She believed it.
هي صدقتها.
Our lives are full of fish swimming backwards.
حياتُنا مليئة بالسمك الذي يسبح للخلف.
We make assumptions and faulty leaps of logic.
نحن نصنع افتراضات وقفزات خاطئة في المنطق.
We harbor bias.
يسايرنا التحييز.
We know that we are right, and they are wrong.
نعلم بأننا على صواب وهم على خطأ.
We fear the worst.
نخشى الأسوأ.
We strive for unattainable perfection.
ونسعى جاهدين لتحقيق الكمال البعيد المنال.
We tell ourselves what we can and cannot do.
نخبر أنفسنا بما نستطيع أن نفعل وما لانستطيع.
In our minds, fish swim by in reverse frantically wagging their heads
بعقولنا ، السمك يسبح عكسياً بهز رأسه باهتياج
and we don't even notice them.
ولا نلاحظه .
I'm going to tell you five facts about myself.
سأخبركم خمس حقائق عني ،
One fact is not true.
حقيقة واحدة هي خاطئة.
One: I graduated from Harvard at 19 with an honors degree in mathematics.
أولاً: تخرجت من هارفرد بعمر 19 بدرجة شرف في الرياضيات.
Two: I currently run a construction company in Orlando.
ثانياً:حالياً أدير شركة بناء في أورلاندو.
Three: I starred on a television sitcom.
ثالثاً:بدأت مسلسلا كوميديا تلفزيونيا.
Four: I lost my sight to a rare genetic eye disease.
رابعاً:فقدت بصري بسبب مرض عيني وراثي نادر.
Five: I served as a law clerk to two US Supreme Court justices.
خامساً:عملت ككاتب عدل لمحكمتين عاليتين في الولايات المتحدة.
Which fact is not true?
أي حقيقة غير صحيحة؟
Actually, they're all true.
بالواقع، جميعها صحيحة.
Yeah. They're all true.
نعم جميعها صحيحة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
At this point, most people really only care about the television show.
عند هذه النقطة أغلب الناس تهتم بالعروض التلفزيونية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I know this from experience.
أعلم هذا من تجربة.
OK, so the show was NBC's "Saved by the Bell: The New Class."
حسناً إذاً العرض كان لNBC "Saved by the Bell: The New Class"
And I played Weasel Wyzell,
ومثلت دور Weasel Wyzell
who was the sort of dorky, nerdy character on the show,
الذي كان نوع شخصيته الأحمق المتحاذق في البرنامج،
which made it a very major acting challenge
الذي جعله تحديا تمثيليا عظيما
for me as a 13-year-old boy.
بالنسبة لي كطفل في الثالثة عشرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, did you struggle with number four, my blindness?
الآن ، هل عانيتم مع الرقم أربعة، فقداني لبصري؟
Why is that?
لماذا هذا؟
We make assumptions about so-called disabilities.
نحن نصنع افتراضات عمايدعى إعاقات.
As a blind man, I confront others' incorrect assumptions
كرجل أعمى ، أواجه الآخرين بمخالفة افتراضاتهم
about my abilities every day.
عن مقدراتي كل يوم.
My point today is not about my blindness, however.
نقطتي اليوم ليست عن فقداني لبصري ولكن،
It's about my vision.
إنها عن بصيرتي.
Going blind taught me to live my life eyes wide open.
أن أكون أعمى علمني أن أعيش حياتي مفتح العينين.
It taught me to spot those backwards-swimming fish
علمني أن ألاحظ السمك الذي يسبح للخلف
that our minds create.
الذي خلقه عقلنا.
Going blind cast them into focus.
أن تصبح أعمى يدفع بهم للتركيز.
What does it feel like to see?
ما هو شعور أن ترى؟
It's immediate and passive.
إنه آني وسلبي.
You open your eyes and there's the world.
تفتح عينيك وهاهنا العالم.
Seeing is believing. Sight is truth.
البصر تصديق .البصيرة هي الحقيقة.
Right?
صحيح؟
Well, that's what I thought.
حسناً، هذا ما اعتقدته.
Then, from age 12 to 25, my retinas progressively deteriorated.
ثم من عمر 12 إلى 25 تدهورت شبكية العين تدريجياً.
My sight became an increasingly bizarre
أصبح بصري غريبا بشكل متزايد
carnival funhouse hall of mirrors and illusions.
قاعة كرنفال مسلية من المرايا والأوهام.
The salesperson I was relieved to spot in a store
البائع ، الذي كنت مرتاحا لأني وجدته في المتجر
was really a mannequin.
كان في الحقيقة تمثال عرض
Reaching down to wash my hands,
انحنيت لأغسل يداي
I suddenly saw it was a urinal I was touching, not a sink,
وفجأة رأيت مبولة كنت ألمسها وليست مغسلة
when my fingers felt its true shape.
عندما رأيت أصابعي بشكلها الحقيقي.
A friend described the photograph in my hand,
صديق لي وصف الصورة التي في يدي
and only then I could see the image depicted.
وحينها فقط أستطيع أن أرى الصورة المرسومة.
Objects appeared, morphed and disappeared in my reality.
تظهر الأشياء وتتحول وتختفي في واقعي.
It was difficult and exhausting to see.
لقد كان من الصعب والمرهق أن أرى.
I pieced together fragmented, transitory images,
جمعت صورا مبعثرة ، صورا عابرة،
consciously analyzed the clues,
حللت الدلائل بوعي
searched for some logic in my crumbling kaleidoscope,
بحثت عن بعض المنطق في مشهدي المتداعي
until I saw nothing at all.
حتى لم أعد أرى شيئا أبداً.
I learned that what we see
تعلمت بأن مانراه
is not universal truth.
ليس حقيقة عالمية.
It is not objective reality.
ليس حقيقة موضوعية.
What we see is a unique, personal, virtual reality
مانراه هو واقع افتراضي شخصي وفريد
that is masterfully constructed by our brain.
بُني بشكل حِرفي من قبل عقلنا.
Let me explain with a bit of amateur neuroscience.
اسمحوا لي أن أشرح قليلا عن علم الأعصاب غير الناضج.
Your visual cortex takes up about 30 percent of your brain.
قشرة الرؤية تأخذ حوالي 30 بالمئة من دماغك.
That's compared to approximately eight percent for touch
هذا مقارنة بتقريب 8 بالمئة للـ اللمس
and two to three percent for hearing.
واثنين إلى ثلاثة بالمئة للسمع.
Every second, your eyes can send your visual cortex
كل ثانية ، عيناك ترسل للقشرة البصرية
as many as two billion pieces of information.
مايصل إلى مليوني جزء من المعلومات.
The rest of your body can send your brain only an additional billion.
الباقي من جسدك يمكن أن يرسل لدماغك فقط بضع بليون إضافي.
So sight is one third of your brain by volume
إذا البصر ثلث الدماغ من حيث الحجم
and can claim about two thirds of your brain's processing resources.
ويمكن أن يستحوذ على ثلثي المواد المعالجة في دماغك.
It's no surprise then
وليس من المفاجئ عندما
that the illusion of sight is so compelling.
يكون الوهم البصري مقنعا للغاية.
But make no mistake about it: sight is an illusion.
فلا نترك مجالاً للخطأ البصر هو وهم.
Here's where it gets interesting.
هنا يصبح الأمر مثيراً.
To create the experience of sight,
عندما يخلق تجربة البصر
your brain references your conceptual understanding of the world,
دماغك يعكس مدى مفهومك للعالم
other knowledge, your memories, opinions, emotions, mental attention.
المعلومات الاخرى، ذكرياتك، آرائك،مشاعرك ،وانتباهك العقلي.
All of these things and far more are linked in your brain to your sight.
وهذه الأشياء وأكثر، مرتبطة في دماغك بالبصر.
These linkages work both ways, and usually occur subconsciously.
هذه الوصلات تعمل باتجاهين وغالباً تحدث بدون وعي.
So for example,
لهذا على سبيل المثال،
what you see impacts how you feel,
عندما ترى انطباعا ماتشعر به
and the way you feel can literally change what you see.
و الطريقة التي تشعر بها بإمكانها حرفياً أن تُغير ماترى.
Numerous studies demonstrate this.
دراسات علم الأعصاب تُظهر هذا.
If you are asked to estimate
إذا سُئلتَ لتُقدر
the walking speed of a man in a video, for example,
مثلاً ، سرعة مشي رجل في مقطع فيديو
your answer will be different if you're told to think about cheetahs or turtles.
جوابك سيكون مختلفا إذا طُلبَ منك أن تفكر بالفهود أو السلاحف.
A hill appears steeper if you've just exercised,
التلة ستبدو أكثر انحداراً إذا كنت قد تدربت للتو،
and a landmark appears farther away
وعلامة النهاية ستبدو أبعد
if you're wearing a heavy backpack.
إذا كنت ترتدي حقيبة ظهر ثقيلة.
We have arrived at a fundamental contradiction.
لقد وصلنا إلى تناقض جوهري.
What you see is a complex mental construction of your own making,
ماتراه تناقض عقلي معقد تخلقه أنت.
but you experience it passively
ولكن تواجهه بشكل سلبي
as a direct representation of the world around you.
كتمثيل مباشر للعالم من حولك.
You create your own reality, and you believe it.
أنت تخلق واقعك وتصدقه.
I believed mine until it broke apart.
لقد صدقت واقعي إلى أن تحطم.
The deterioration of my eyes shattered the illusion.
تدهور عيناي بدد الوهم.
You see, sight is just one way
كما ترون، البصر هو طريقة واحدة
we shape our reality.
إننا نصوغ واقعنا.
We create our own realities in many other ways.
بإمكاننا أن نخلق واقعنا بالكثير من الطرق.
Let's take fear as just one example.
لنأخذ الخوف ، على سبيل المثال
Your fears distort your reality.
مخاوفك تشوّه واقعك.
Under the warped logic of fear, anything is better than the uncertain.
تحت منطق مشوّه من الخوف أي شيء أفضل من الغير مؤكد.
Fear fills the void at all costs,
الخوف يملأ الفراغ بأي ثمن،
passing off what you dread for what you know,
ويمرر ماترهبه فوق ماتعرفه،
offering up the worst in place of the ambiguous,
وتقديم الأسوأ مكان الغامض،
substituting assumption for reason.
تبديل الافتراضات لسبب.
Psychologists have a great term for it: awfulizing.
علماء النفس لديهم مصطلح رائع لهذا :الترويع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Right?
صحيح؟
Fear replaces the unknown with the awful.
الخوف يُبدل الغير معروف بالمروّع.
Now, fear is self-realizing.
الآن الخوف هو تحقيق الذات
When you face the greatest need
عندما تواجه أعظم حاجة
to look outside yourself and think critically,
بأن تنظر خارج نفسك وتُفكر بشكل نقدي
fear beats a retreat deep inside your mind,
الخوف يتغلب على التراجع في عقلك الباطن،
shrinking and distorting your view,
يُقلص ويشوّه رؤيتك،
drowning your capacity for critical thought
يُغرق قدرتك على التفكير النقدي
with a flood of disruptive emotions.
بسيل من العواطف المدمرة.
When you face a compelling opportunity to take action,
عندما تواجه فرصة مُلحة بأن تأخذ المبادرة
fear lulls you into inaction,
الخوف يهدئك لتتقاعس عن العمل،
enticing you to passively watch its prophecies fulfill themselves.
يغريك بشكل سلبي لتشاهد نبوائته التي ستتحقق.
When I was diagnosed with my blinding disease,
عندما تم تشخيصي بمرض العمى،
I knew blindness would ruin my life.
علمت بأن العمى سيدمر حياتي.
Blindness was a death sentence for my independence.
العمى كان حكم إعدام على استقلالي.
It was the end of achievement for me.
لقد كان نهاية الإنجازات بالنسبة لي.
Blindness meant I would live an unremarkable life,
العمى كان يعني بأني سأعيش حياة غير ملحوظة
small and sad,
صغيرة وحزينة،
and likely alone.
وعلى الأغلب وحيدا.
I knew it.
لقد كنت أعلم هذا.
This was a fiction born of my fears, but I believed it.
لقد كان هذا وهما توّلد من الخوف ولكن أنا صدقته.
It was a lie, but it was my reality,
كان كذبة ولكن كان واقعي.
just like those backwards-swimming fish in little Dorothy's mind.
كسمكة دورثي التي تسبح للخلف في عقلها.
If I had not confronted the reality of my fear,
إذا لم أواجه حقيقة خوفي،
I would have lived it.
لكنت عشتها.
I am certain of that.
أنا متأكد من ذلك.
So how do you live your life eyes wide open?
إذاً كيف يمكنك أن تعيش حياتك بعيون مفتوحة؟
It is a learned discipline.
إنه انضباط مكتسب.
It can be taught. It can be practiced.
بالإمكان تعلمه، بالإمكان ممارسته.
I will summarize very briefly.
سأُلخص باختصار شديد.
Hold yourself accountable
استمر بمساءلة نفسك
for every moment, every thought,
في كل لحظة في كل فكرة،
every detail.
وكل تفصيل.
See beyond your fears.
شاهد ماخلف مخاوفك.
Recognize your assumptions.
تعرّف على الافتراضات الخاصة بك.
Harness your internal strength.
استغل قوتك الداخلية.
Silence your internal critic.
اسكت نقدك الداخلي.
Correct your misconceptions about luck and about success.
صحح اعتقاداتك الخاطئة عن الحظ والنجاح.
Accept your strengths and your weaknesses, and understand the difference.
تقبل قوتك وضعفك ، و افهم الفرق.
Open your hearts
افتحوا قلوبكم
to your bountiful blessings.
لنعمكم الوفيرة.
Your fears, your critics,
مخاوفكم ونُقادكم،
your heroes, your villains --
أبطالكم والأوغاد--
they are your excuses,
إنها اعذاركم،
rationalizations, shortcuts,
المسوغات والاختصارات،
justifications, your surrender.
المبررات والاستسلام.
They are fictions you perceive as reality.
إنها خيالات تتصوره حقيقة.
Choose to see through them.
اختر أن ترى عبرها.
Choose to let them go.
اختر بأن تدعها تختفي.
You are the creator of your reality.
أنت الذي تخلق واقعك
With that empowerment comes complete responsibility.
وبتمكين هذا تأتي المسؤولية.
I chose to step out of fear's tunnel into terrain uncharted and undefined.
اخترت الخروج من نفق الخوف إلى أماكن مجهولة وغير معروفة.
I chose to build there a blessed life.
اخترت ان أبني هناك حياة مُنَعمة.
Far from alone,
أبعد بكثير من أن أكون وحيدا،
I share my beautiful life with Dorothy,
أشارك حياتي الرائعة مع دورثي،
my beautiful wife,
زوجتي الجميلة،
with our triplets, whom we call the Tripskys,
ومع ثلاث توائم الذين نسميهم tripskys،
and with the latest addition to the family,
ومع إضافتنا الجديدة لعائلتنا
sweet baby Clementine.
طفلتي الحلوة كليمنتاين.
What do you fear?
ما الذي تخشاه؟
What lies do you tell yourself?
ما الأكاذيب التي تخبر بها نفسك؟
How do you embellish your truth and write your own fictions?
كيف يمكنك أن تُزين حقيقتك وتكتب خيالك؟
What reality are you creating for yourself?
ماهو الواقع الذي تخلقه لنفسك؟
In your career and personal life, in your relationships,
في عملك وفي حياتك الشخصية، في علاقاتك،
and in your heart and soul,
في قلبك وروحك،
your backwards-swimming fish do you great harm.
سمكتك التي تسبح للخلف تخلق لك ضرراً كبيراً.
They exact a toll in missed opportunities and unrealized potential,
خسائر الفرص الضائعة و الإمكانيات الغير مستغلة،
and they engender insecurity and distrust
توّلد انعدام الأمان وانعدام الثقة
where you seek fulfillment and connection.
حيث تبحث إثبات الذات والتواصل.
I urge you to search them out.
أن أحثكم أن تبحثوا عنهم .
Helen Keller said that the only thing worse than being blind
هيلين كلير قالت الشيء الوحيد الأسوأ في كونك أعمى
is having sight but no vision.
هو أن يكون لديك بصر ولا تمتلك البصيرة.
For me, going blind was a profound blessing,
بالنسبة لي ، أن أصبح أعمى كانت نعمه عميقة.
because blindness gave me vision.
لأن العمى أعطاني البصيرة.
I hope you can see what I see.
أتمنى أن تروا ما استطيع رؤيته.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Isaac, before you leave the stage, just a question.
برونو جيوساني إسحاق سؤال فقط قبل أن تغادر المسرح
This is an audience of entrepreneurs, of doers, of innovators.
هذا حضور من رواد الأعمال ، الفاعلين، ومن المخترعين.
You are a CEO of a company down in Florida,
أنت مدير عام لشركة تقع في فلوريدا،
and many are probably wondering,
والعديد احتمال أن يتسائلوا
how is it to be a blind CEO?
ماهو حال أن تكون مديرا عاما أعمى؟
What kind of specific challenges do you have, and how do you overcome them?
ما هو نوع التحديات بشكل خاص التي تعاني منها ، وكيف تتغلب عليها؟
Isaac Lidsky: Well, the biggest challenge became a blessing.
حسناً، أكبر تحدي أصبح نعمة.
I don't get visual feedback from people.
لا أحصل من الناس على تغذية راجعة بالنسبة للرؤية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
BG: What's that noise there? IL: Yeah.
-ما هذه الضجة هناك؟ -نعم.
So, for example, in my leadership team meetings,
إذاً على سبيل المثال، في قيادتي للقاءات الفريق
I don't see facial expressions or gestures.
لا أستطيع أن أرى تعابير الوجوه أو إيماءات.
I've learned to solicit a lot more verbal feedback.
تعلمت أن ألتمس الكثير من ردود الفعل اللفظية.
I basically force people to tell me what they think.
بشكل عام أجبر الناس أن يخبروني ماذا يفكرون.
And in this respect,
وبهذا الصدد ،
it's become, like I said, a real blessing for me personally and for my company,
أصبحت كما قلت نعمة حقيقية بالنسبة لي شخصياً ولشركتي.
because we communicate at a far deeper level,
لأننا نتواصل بشكل أعمق
we avoid ambiguities,
نتجنب الغموض،
and most important, my team knows that what they think truly matters.
وبشكل أهم فريقي يعلم بأن مايفكرون به مهم للغاية.
BG: Isaac, thank you for coming to TED. IL: Thank you, Bruno.
-إسحاق شكراً لك لمجيئكم إلى TED -شكراً لك برونو.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)